[MUSIC]
[科學哲學]
In this lecture we'll talk
about Philosophy of Science.
這一講來談談「科學哲學」。
I'll give a brief overview of
the history of Philosophy of Science.
我將簡單介紹科學哲學的歷史。
Now this is a topic that you
can spend an entire course on.
這個主題應該用好幾堂課來談
If you are interested,
I highly recommend you do this.
如果你有興趣建議去選修相關課程
But you should at least know the basics.
這一講只提一些基本課題
Can we ever have something
that's objectively true?
像是我們能對事物做出客觀真實的論斷？
Do we know whether something
is a science or not?
我們能判別科學與偽科學嗎？
These are important questions to consider.
都是值得思考的問題。
Now if we ask ourselves the question,
what makes something scientific?
首先想想這個問題：什麼造就了科學？
Then we are asking,
what is the demarcation criteria?
接著可以問：科學有沒有清楚的界線？
What differentiates between science and
pseudoscience?
科學與偽科學有何差異？
Do you think that astrology
is a scientific discipline?
你認為占星術是科學的一部分嗎？
Should we use tax money to
fund research on astrology?
人民的稅金可以用來補助占星術的研究嗎？
Do you think that precognition, studying
whether we can predict the future or
可以補助探索人類有沒有預見未來能力的超感知覺研究嗎？
not is a science and
should we fund it based on tax money?
可以補助探索人類有沒有預見未來能力的超感知覺研究嗎？
Do you think that my own discipline,
experimental psychology is a science and
或者我安身立命的實驗心理學才是真正的科學
should we fund this?
才值得補助？
You see that the question whether
something is a science or
這些問題點出了解一項研究是不是科學，
not has real life consequences.
會對現實生活造成影響
If we think about demarcation criteria,
then different people have different
然而劃分科學與偽科學的界線
opinions about whether we can say that
there's a difference between science and
人人心中各有一把尺。
pseudoscience.
人人心中各有一把尺
Popper says that if a theory is
falsifiable, then it's scientific and
波普(Popper)的劃分標準是理論能不能被否證
this is the demarcation
criteria according to Popper.
波普(Popper)的劃分標準是理論能不能被否證
But not everybody agrees.
不過並非人人同意他的看法
For example, Lakatos says that a given
fact is explained scientifically
像是他的學生拉卡托斯(Lakatos)認為除非理論能正確預測新事實，對舊事實的解釋才是科學的。
only if a new fact is predicted with it.
You should not just describe things
that you see, but your new descriptions
科學研究不能只描述現在看到的事物
也要描述
are scientific explanations when
they can also predict new things.
能預測的事物，以及新的事實
When they can explain new information.
There are also people who give up on
trying to differentiate between science
也有人主張沒有必要區分科學與偽科學
and pseudoscience.
Well known example is Paul Feyerabend,
he says that given any rule,
像是波普的另一位學生費耶阿本德(Feyerabend)認為
there are always circumstances when it is
advisable not only to ignore the rule, but
總會出現反對現存規範的案例
to adopt its opposite.
So there's never rule that you can follow
that will differentiate between science
所以不存在能準確劃分科學與偽科學的標準
and pseudoscience, anything goes.
他的名言是”諸行皆可“(anything goes)。
If we draw in inferences from data,
then there are logical ways to do this and
根據資料做推論，有邏輯與非邏輯的方法
illogical ways to do this.
In propositional logic, one valid rule of
inference is known as the Modus Tollens.
能做有效推論的一種邏輯方法是否定後件(Modus Tollens)
In other words, denying the consequents.
簡單說就是否定推論得到的結果
Let's take a look.
If the Modus Tollens is used we have
a line of reasoning that goes as this.
否定後件能寫成這樣的形式
If p then q, not q, therefore not p.
若p則q，非q
所以非p
Let's make it a little bit more concrete.
來看看這條規則的實際用處
If we have a theory,
then we should observe some data.
根據要驗證的理論，我們收集需要的資料
Then we collect some data but we do not
observe the data that we predicted.
但是收集到的資料不符合理論的預測
From this we can deny the consequent,
therefore not the theory.
根據否定後件的規則，推論理論不成立
A very often illogical way of drawing
inferences is known as affirming
另一方面就是採取非邏輯方法
從肯定的角度進行推論
the consequent.
另一方面就是採取非邏輯方法
從肯定的角度進行推論
Now this is not a valid rule of
inference although it's tempting to use.
雖然這種方法有時有用
卻非有效的推論規則
It goes like this,
if p then q we observe q therefore p.
寫成邏輯形式就是
若p則q，觀察到q，所以p成立。
Now this might look like it's logical but
it isn't.
雖然這像是邏輯規則，其實不是
Let's look at some more detail.
讓我告訴你為什麼
If we have a theory then we
should observe some data,
為了確認手上理論為真，我們必須收集資料
we observe the data and then we conclude
that therefore the theory is true.
收集到的資料要用來確認理論為真
Now this might still look
like it's valid but it isn't.
這樣的命題推理似乎有效，其實不然
Let's make it even more concrete.
讓我用更明確的例子
Let's say that I conclude that if
I'm a man then I'm also a human.
我說“若我是男人，那我也是人類”
I observe that I am a human and then I
conclude that therefore I must be a man,
我觀察到我是人類，所以結論我是男人
but this last step is not valid.
這樣的推論其實無效
I could also be a woman or
anything in between.
因為我也可以是女人或跨性別者
A theory can be either refuted or
corroborated but
一個理論可以被證明為錯，或有證據證成
you can never prove a theory.
但不能直接推論為真
Now this is important.
這個認識很重要
We can never have certain knowledge.
我們不會有肯定的知識
We can aim for it but
we can never achieve it.
這個目標可以努力但永遠無法達成
It's easier to refute a theory and this is
based on Popper's idea of falsification.
波普的否證論概念就是證明理論為錯較容易
So you can have a conclusion
where you falsify a prediction.
只要否證一個預測就會有結論
For example, if we look at the prediction,
all swans are white, now, no number
例如這一則預測：
所有天鵝都是白的，就算不知道白天鵝有多少隻
of sightings of white swans can ever prove
the theory that all swans are white.
永遠可以宣稱這個預測為真
However, if we only see one black swan,
但是，只要今天看見一隻黑天鵝
this will disprove our theory
that all swans are white.
這個預測就會被推翻
So you see that falsification is
a very potent tool to reject theories.
由此可見否證論推翻理論的威力
Now we can never accept them, we can
observe observations that are in line with
反過來說，即使無法完全證明理論為真，
our theory but we can never prove it.
只要獲得的資料與預測一致，理論還是可能為真
However, when we use inferences
based on statistics,
然而在統計推論的場域
then falsifications are never really black
or white, as the case with black swans.
並不像黑天鵝問題一樣有非黑即白的否證
If you see a black swan and
you have a clear view,
看見黑天鵝是鐵錚錚的否證證據
then you can be pretty sure
that this is not a white swan.
看見黑天鵝是鐵錚錚的否證證據
You might even get a feather and try to
wash it, see that the black doesn't come
如果你很龜毛，可能會洗洗看
黑天鵝的羽毛會不會掉色
off and then you have a solid
observation that black swans exist.
再決定要不要接受這個證據
In statistics we always
work with probabilities.
統計則是依賴機率
We have a certain probability that the
data we have observed, is surprising for
資料的否證程度全賴歸察到的機率
example.
We have a certain probability
that there is no true effect.
只能斷言沒有真實效果的機率
Now this kind of statements
are never completely black or white.
這樣的結論永遠不會非黑即白
So it's always more difficult
to falsify a prediction.
所以任何統計的預測被否證的難度頗高
Furthermore, we wonder whether we
actually reject theories after
更進一步的說，理論很難被一種否證證據推翻
a single falsification.
And Lakatos argues that we never do this.
拉卡托斯指出不可能有這樣的否證
People have some sort of feeling for
a theory.
想出理論的方式有很多種
They like a specific theory and
they want it to be true.
有的理論的目標很特定
And this is perfectly fine.
只要不被特定的證據推翻就好
You can try to find support for
it in different ways.
支持理論的證據也是各式各樣
Now there are good reasons
to stick with the theory.
測試理論會不會被推翻其實很有意義
When a theory makes a very, very good
predictions then a single observation
如果能用理論做個好預測
that's not in line with your predictions
is no reason to give up the entire theory.
然後獲得不支持理論預測的證據
就可以毫無懸念的放棄理論。
This statement by Stevens is rather nice.
Stevens的這段話說得很好
It says, the lesson of history is that
a bold and plausible theory that fills
科學史上有許多大膽又合理的理論
a scientific need is seldom broken by the
impact of contrary facts and arguments.
被反證的事實與言論擊倒
Only with an alternative theory can
we hope to displace a defective one.
而且總是有新的理論取代舊理論的位置
So it's perfectly fine if you
sometimes observe a finding
如果你能發現和你的理論預測不同的證據其實是好事
that's not in line with
theoretical predictions.
如果你能發現和你的理論預測不同的證據其實是好事
You don't have to throw your
theory out of the window.
你不必直接捨棄理論。
If you have a strong theory that makes
good predictions in other fields,
如果原來理論的預測在其他地方經得起考驗
there's no reason to give it up
until you have a better theory.
依然可以堅持到有更好的理論出現
So if there's a falsification,
如果理論的預測被否證
if one of these predictions don't hold
up then what is exactly falsified?
代表理論本身被否證嗎？
Is it the theory itself or
there are auxiliary theories.
被否證的是理論本體還是附屬命題？
Assumptions that you make about the data
collection process, for example.
設想你做了一次資料收集
Now let's say you do
an experiment on some people and
像是根據一個理論預測，找些人做了實驗
you have a theoretical prediction.
And it's not supported by the data.
不過結果不符合預測
Now you can either distrust your
theory itself or you can say,
此時可以捨棄這套理論
well maybe something else that I assumed
was going on didn't happen as I predicted.
也可以認為實驗過程沒有做好
For example, maybe your
participants were very, very tired.
像是找到的參與者精神狀態都很差
They didn't process all
the information you provided.
無法處理好實驗過程中的訊息
And as a consequence, you didn't
observe the effect that you predicted.
以致於結果不如預期
Now in these situations,
you might not throw away your theory.
若是如此
還不必拋棄理論
You might say,
你可以說
well some of the assumption that I made
about how much attention participants were
是因為實驗操作不符合理論中注意力集中的前提
paying to the experiments,
those assumptions are violated.
需要再試一次
Let's try it again, let's try to boost
the attention levels of participants and
看看注意力集中的參與者表現
see if we can find the expected effect.
會不會符合預測
According to Lakatos, we have a core
theory and around this core theory there's
拉卡托斯主張理論有不可更改的硬核
protective belt of auxiliary hypotheses,
these are assumptions that you make about
以及可調整假設命題的保護帶
the research process and you can give up
some of these assumptions or change them.
研究者可以在過程中修改或放棄保護帶的某些命題
In this sense, you can keep your
core theory, even if your prediction
這樣的主張指出，
若是為了做出更好的預測
doesn't pan out by changing some
of the assumptions that you make.
而調整部分假設，還是能保留硬核
Now, of course, when you do this,
但是如此一來
you enter what's known as
a degenerative research line.
就會進入「退化性研究進程」
It's fine to make an ad hoc assumption
saying, well, it's true but only if.
有時為了提高預測力而提出增加可能條件的後設假設
But if you have to keep doing this and
keep doing this,
但長久為之，理論將不再能提出新的預測
then your theory is not
making new predictions.
但長久為之，理論將不再能提出新的預測
There are no new facts that are predicted
with the theory that you make.
因為這樣的理論無法預測並解釋新的事實
You're just trying to change the theory
只能持續存活到失敗的預測無法修補為止
every time when a failed
prediction emerges.
只能持續存活到失敗的預測無法修補為止
What you ideally want is to turn this
into a progressive research line.
有生命的理論應是處於「進化性研究進程」
A first failed test is perfectly fine.
第一次測試失敗不打緊
You can slightly change your theory or
one of the assumptions you're making, but
只改變少數假設
then this should lead to
a progressive research line,
就能推進到進化性研究進程是最好的
there should be new facts that you can
predict with your improved theory.
如此的理論能持續預測新事實
When this is not the case,
it's perfectly fine to keep trying but
就算持續修正還是無法預測新事實的理論
after a while, you enter a research
line that's not giving anything new,
就算持續修正還是無法預測新事實的理論
which happened with astrology in the past.
曾在天文學歷史出現過
So according to Lakatos, something like
astrology would not be a scientific
拉卡托斯認為無法保持進化性研究進程的天文學理論
discipline because it never turned
into a progressive research line.
不能算是科學理論
They're only ad hoc changes to the theory
every time when a failed prediction
只是一堆失敗預測堆成的補丁式理論。
emerges.
Now there are some people
who doubt whether we can
很多唸過科學哲學的人會問有沒有客觀科學存在？
have an objective science altogether.
So they say the quest for
an objective truth is a nice try, but
有人主張這尋找客觀事實是高尚的目標
we'll never really reach it.
但是沒有達成的一日
One of them is Thomas Kuhn in his book
The Structure of Scientific Revolutions.
湯馬斯孔恩是其中一人
他的名著“科學革命的結構”
He says that observations are always
theory laden, not objective.
就提到任何觀察都帶有理論的觀點，並非客觀
There's no such thing as
an objective view at the world.
世上沒有絕對客觀的立場
We always look at the world
with certain assumptions and
我們總是帶著某個理論色彩的眼鏡看這個世界
科學研究也不例外
these assumptions color the way
that we do our research.
我們總是帶著某個理論色彩的眼鏡看這個世界
科學研究也不例外
He goes as far as to say,
孔恩又提到
that the proponents of competing paradigms
practice their trades in different worlds.
相互對抗的典範支持者在各自的世界中交流
What he means is that it's possible for
也就是說
researchers to have different
theoretical backgrounds and
理論背景各異的研究者
they will look at the world in completely
different ways that you cannot unify.
只關注與自己有關的資訊
不會互相往來
He talks about how people
practice puzzle-solving science,
他以應該是科學進展主力的基礎科學為例
which is basically normal science
as science should progress.
說明科學家如何解決難題
And this is followed by a paradigm shift,
a revolution in science, and after
隨著典範轉移，開始發生科學革命
such a scientific revolution, we look at
the world in a completely different way.
在革命之後，世人觀看世界的眼光徹底改變
And after a scientific revolution we
cannot interpret the data that we
像是革命之後推論資料的方式
collected before this paradigm shift.
與典範轉移之前完全不同
Things completely change.
世界會改變
So there's no objective knowledge.
所以沒有客觀的知識
Things always depend on the specific
paradigm that you're in.
何為真實全看你所憑依的典範
According to Kuhn,
science is not cumulative, but
孔恩認為科學進展不是累積的
it's revolutionary,
based on subjective reasons.
而是基於主觀理由發動的革命
These can be social norms or
idyllic ideas that people have.
就像是大眾遵守的社會規範或共同理念也會改變
So it's not that science will always just
progress and become better and better,
科學進展的方向不一定是越來越好
the idea that Lakatos is expressing
in his progressive research lines,
但不像拉卡托斯的研究進程說法
no instead, there's just
a revolution every now and then.
孔恩認為是週而復始的革命造成
And we have a completely different
paradigm within which we practice science.
才會產生前後不一樣的科學操作典範
Modern few points on philosophy of science
acknowledge that scientific knowledge is
現代科學哲學的論點讓我們了解
科學知識也是一種社會產物
a social product.
現代科學哲學的論點讓我們了解
科學知識也是一種社會產物
For example, Helen Longino talks about how
we have no objective knowledge, but there
像Helen Longino認為就算沒有客觀知識
is only intersubjective criticism, what
constitutes the objectivity of science.
互為主體的批判也能構成科學的客觀性
So there's no objectivity outside of
the social enterprise that science is.
但這種客觀性不能自外於科學所存在的社會體系
What's important, according to Longino,
is public avenues for
Longino還強調批判的公眾性
criticism, for example peer review, when
you submit your paper for publication.
像是投稿期刊的同儕評審
What's important is that there is room for
peers to criticize your finding or
讓同行專家有空間批判或改善彼此的作品
improve it if possible.
There should be shared standards, we
should have some idea of what we're doing.
還有共同遵守的標準
科學家有行事的一致信念
A tool set that we use
to evaluate evidence.
還有可共同評估證據的方法
There should be open reevaluation.
此外還應該有公開的自省機制
So if there's criticism and
there are new insights,
一旦批評帶來新的洞見
a scientific discipline should change.
科學社群應該改變
Again, this is not something
that happens in astrology.
就像過去天文學的改變並非一天之內發生
There's enough criticism on astrology but
而是經歷幾十年批判的累積
it never really changed
in the last decades.
而是經歷幾十年批判的累積
And finally, what's important for
最後
this social intersubjective objectivity
is that there's equality within peers.
互為主體的社會化客觀性強調同儕之間的平等
If you have an informed
researcher that knows what he or
如果研究是共同合作
she is doing, then these people should
have equality in their interaction.
成員之間的互動應該是平等的
It should not be the case that
one person can determine,
不該有一個人決定研究如何進行
this is how it's going to be because
I'm the most powerful individual here.
只因為其中的一位成員有較大的權勢
In this lecture we briefly talked
about philosophy of science and
這一講簡單介紹科學哲學
different perspectives that philosophers
have on what makes something scientific.
和不同哲學家認為科學是什麼的觀點
Personally I think,
the idea of a progressive and
我自己從進化及退化的科學進程受益良多
a degenerative research
line is quite useful.
我自己從進化及退化的科學進程受益良多
When you make a prediction that
doesn't pan out, you're in trouble,
若是結果不符合預測，得費更多力氣
you have to try to turn this into
a progressive research line in the future.
將這門研究推向進化性研究進程
But overall,
總而言之
there's no clear single answer on whether
we can ever have objective knowledge.
世上有沒有客觀知識並沒有清楚的答案
[MUSIC]
影片結束